Curriculum Vitae

Erlend Dancke Sandorf, PhD

11-08-1987 Date of birth Nationality

Norwegian

Norwegian (native), English (fluent), German (basic) Languages

erlend.dancke.sandorf :at: nmbu.no https://edsandorf.me

Website orcid.org/0000-0001-7521-4773 ORCID

Research interests and expertise

My research focuses on non-market valuation of ecosystem services. In particular, the use of advanced discrete choice models to accommodate non-utility maximizing behavior, and the use of simplifying strategies and heuristics. I have developed and utilized models that consider simplifying strategies such as attribute non-attendance, elimination-by-aspects and satisficing.

Software expertise: Ox, R, Matlab, NGENE, LaTeX, Microsoft Office

Work experience

Current position

E-mail

Nov 2020 - present Post-doctoral researcher

Norwegian University of Life Sciences, School of Economics and Busi-

ness

Previous positions

Nov 2018 - Oct 2020 Marie Skłodowska-Curie Research Fellow

University of Stirling, Stirling Management School, Economics Divi-

sion, Stirling, United Kingdom

Nov 2016 - Oct 2018 Post-doctoral researcher

Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Department of For-

est Economics, Centre for Environmental and Resource Economics,

Umeå, Sweden

Nov 2012 - Oct 2016 PhD Candidate

UiT - The Arctic University of Norway, Faculty of Biosciences, Fish-

eries and Economics, The Norwegian College of Fishery Science,

Tromsø, Norway

Education

Nov 2012 – Aug 2016 Ph.D. Environmental and Resource Economics

UiT - The Arctic University of Norway, Faculty of Biosciences, Fisheries and Economics, The Norwegian College of Fishery Science **Thesis:** "Valuing unfamiliar and complex ecosystem services - The influence of survey mode, knowledge and dishonesty"

Aug 2010 – Jun 2012 M.Sc. Business Administration

The Norwegian University of Life Sciences, School of Economics and Business

Thesis: "Recycling as a private contribution to a public good: The effect of consistent and inconsistent information on the recycling decision"

Aug 2007 – Jun 2010 B.Sc. Business Administration

The Norwegian University of Life Sciences, School of Economics and Business

Publications

Peer reviewed scientific journals

- 12 Campbell, D. & **Sandorf, E. D.**, 2020, The use of latent variable models in policy: A road fraught with peril?, *Bio-based and Applied Economics*, accepted
- 11 Chorus, C., van Cranenburgh, S., Daniel, A., **Sandorf, E. D.**, Sobhani, A. & Szep, T., 2020, Obfuscation maximization-based decision making: Theory, methodology and first empirical evidence, *Mathematical Social Sciences*, accepted
- 10 Xuan, B. B. & Sandorf, E. D., 2020, Potential for sustainable aquaculture: Insights from discrete choice experiments, *Environmental and Resource Economics*, 77:401-421
- 9 **Sandorf, E. D.**, Persson, L. & Broberg, T., 2020, Using an integrated choice and latent variable model to understand the impact of "professional" respondents in a stated preference survey, *Resource and Energy Economics*, 61
- 8 Armstrong, C. W, Aanesen, M., van Rensburg, T. M. & Sandorf, E. D., 2019, Willingness to pay to protect cold water corals, *Conservation Biology*, 33(6):1329-1337
- 7 **Sandorf, E. D.**, 2018, Did you miss something? Inattentive respondents in discrete choice experiments, *Environmental and Resource Economics*, 73(4):1197-1235
- 6 **Sandorf, E. D.** & Campbell, D., 2018, Accommodating satisficing behavior in stated choice experiments, *European Review of Agricultural Economics*, 46(1):133-162
- 5 Daniel, A., Persson, L. & **Sandorf, E. D.**, 2018, Accounting for elimination-by-aspects strategies and demand management in electricity contract choice, *Energy Economics*, 73:80-90

Publications (continued)

- 4 Sandorf, E. D. Crastes dit Sourd, R. & Mahieu, 2018, Left to right line by line: The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on preferences and processing strategies, *Journal of Choice Modelling*, 29:113-132
- 3 Xuan, B. B., **Sandorf, E. D.** & Aanesen, M., 2017, Informing management strategies for a reserve: Results from a discrete choice experiment survey, *Ocean and Coastal Management*, 145:35-43
- 2 Sandorf, E. D., Campbell, D. & Hanley, N., 2016, Disentangling the influence of knowledge on attribute non-attendance, *Journal of Choice Modelling*, 24:36-50
- Sandorf, E. D., Aanesen, M. & Navrud, S., 2016, Valuing unfamiliar and complex environmental goods: A comparison of valuation workshops and internet panel surveys with videos, *Ecological Economics*, 129:50-61

Software

- 2 Sandorf, E. E., 2019, cmdlR: Choice Modeling in R, R package, URL: https://github.com/edsandorf/cmdlR
- Sandorf, E. D., Chorus, C. & van Cranenburgh, S., 2019, obfuscatoR: Obfuscation Game Designs, R package, URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=obfuscatoR

Awards and Honors

- The European Association of Agricultural Economists' "Best Paper Award for 2019" for publications in the European Review of Agricultural Economics for the paper: Accommodating satisficing behavior in stated choice experiments. Co-authored by Danny Campbell.
- 2017 Best paper award for the paper "The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on preferences and processing strategies"

 Workshop on Non-Market Valuation (WONV), 26th 27th of June, University of Leeds, Leeds, United Kingdom

Grants and Funding

The Influence of Information Search on Preference Formation and Choice (INSPiRE)

Funder: Horizon 2020 - Marie Skłodowska-Curie Individual Fellowship No. 793163

Period: 2018 - 2020 Amount: EUR 183,454.80 My role: Principal investigator

Grants and Funding (continued)

2018 Producer and consumer preferences for sustainable shrimp aquaculture policy in Vietnam

Funder: NAFOSTED project nr. 502.99-2018.25

Period: 2018 - 2020

Amount: USD 28,000.00 (EUR 24,500.00)

My role: Co-investigator

Travel grant to participate in the Emerging Leaders program during the Arctic Frontiers 2015 conference

Funder: Research Council of Norway

Period: Jan 2015

Amount: NOK 30,000.00 (EUR 3,000.00)

My role: Personal travel grant

Conferences, workshops and seminars

Invited presentations

2019 Invited seminar

When: 31st of May

Where: University of Aberdeen, Health Economics Research Group Title: "The search for something better - a consideration set model"

2018 Invited seminar

When: 14th of June

Where: Technical University of Delft, Transport and Logistics Group, Delft, The

Netherlands

Title: "Satisficing in discrete choice experiments – some possibilities"

2018 16th Berlin DCE Colloquium

When: 12th of June

Where: Technical University of Berlin, Berlin, Germany

Title: "Incorporating non-RUM decision rules into the analysis of discrete choice

experiments"

2018 Invited seminar

When: 15th of March

Where: University of Nantes, LEMNA, Nantes, France

Title: "The effect of attribute-alternative-matrix displays on preferences and process-

ing strategies"

2018 Invited seminar

When: 8th of February

Where: University of Leeds, Institute for Transport Studies, Leeds, United Kingdom

Title: "Assessing the impact of 'professional' respondents using an integrated choice

and latent variable model"

Conferences, workshops and seminars (continued)

2017 Invited seminar

When: 27th of March

Where: University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, Sweden

Title: "Trapped! Catching inattentive respondents in an online discrete choice exper-

iment"

Conference and workshop presentations

2020 Annual Conference of the European Association of Environmental and Resource

Economists (EAERE)

When: 23rd of June - 3rd of July

Where: Organized online

Title: "An information search approach to discrete choice analysis"

2019 ENVECHO VIII Workshop

When: 30th of September - 1st of October

Where: University of Verona, Verona, Italy

Title: "Identifying consideration sets through search an implementation using Shiny"

2019 6th International Choice Modelling Conference (ICMC)

When: 19th - 21st of August

Where: Kobe, Japan

Title: "An information search approach to discrete choice analysis"

2019 LEEP Conference 2019 (LEEPin2019)

When: 24^{th} - 25^{th} of June

Where: University of Exeter Business School, Exeter, United Kingdom

Title (Poster): "The effect of device experience and time of day on stated preferences"

2018 6th World Congress for Environmental and Resource Economists (WCERE)

When: 25th - 29th of June

Where: University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, Sweden

Title: "Assessing the impact of 'professional' respondents using an integrated choice

and latent variable model"

2018 25th Ulvön Conference on Environmental Economics

When: 19th - 21st of June

Where: Ulvön, Sweden

Title: "Assessing the impact of 'professional' respondents using an integrated choice

and latent variable model"

2017 ENVECHO VI Workshop

When: 25^{th} - 26^{th} of September

Where: University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland

Title: "The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on preferences and process-

ing strategies"

Conferences, workshops and seminars (continued)

2017 Workshop on Non-Market Valuation (WONV)

When: 26th - 27th of June

Where: University of Leeds, Institute for Transport Studies, Leeds, United Kingdom Title: "The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on preferences and processing strategies"

ing strategies"

2017 24th Ulvön Conference on Environmental Economics

When: 20th - 22nd of June Where: Ulvön, Sweden

Title: "The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on preferences and process-

ing strategies"

2017 International Choice Modeling Conference (ICMC)

When: $3^{\rm rd}$ - $5^{\rm th}$ of April

Where: University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa

Title: "Thats good enough! Satisficing in Stated Choice Experiments"

2016 Workshop on Non-Market Valuation (WONV)

When: 20th - 21st of June Where: Bordeaux, France

Title: "Dishonest Respondents in Discrete Choice Experiments - An Example using

a Probability Based Internet Panel"

2016 Experiments for Environmental Policy Formation Workshop

When: 14th of April

Where: University of Stirling, Stirling, United Kingdom

Title: "Dishonest Respondents in Discrete Choice Experiments - An Example using

a Probability Based Internet Panel"

2016 Annual Meeting of the Norwegian Association of Economists

When: 4^{th} - 5_{th} of January

Where: Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Trondheim, Norway

Title: "Dishonest Respondents in Discrete Choice Experiments - An Example using

a Probability Based Internet Panel"

2015 Annual Conference of the European Association of Environmental and Resource

Economists (EAERE) When: 24th - 26th of June

Where: University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland

Title: "Disentangling the Influence of Knowledge on Processing Strategies in Discrete

Choice Experiments"

2015 International Choice Modeling Conference (ICMC)

When: 10^{th} - 13^{th} of Mav

Where: University of Texas, Austin, TX, USA

Title: "Disentangling the Influence of Knowledge on Processing Strategies in Discrete

Choice Experiments"

Conferences, workshops and seminars (continued)

2015 Annual Meeting of the Norwegian Association of Economists

When: 5^{th} - 6_{th} of January

Where: University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway

Title: "Survey Mode Effects: Comparing Valuation Workshops and an Online Panel"

2014 Scottish Choice Modelling Conference

When: 16th

Where: University of Stirling, Stirling, United Kingdom

Title: "Survey Mode Effects: Valuation Workshops versus Online Panels"

2014 Annual BIOECON Conference

When: 21^{st} - 23_{rd} of September

Where: Kings College, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom

Title: "Reliable Estimates? Evidence form a Discrete Choice Experiment on Cold

Water Corals in Norway"

2014 International Conference of the International Institute of Fisheries Economics and

Trade (IIFET)

When: 7^{th} - 11_{th} of July

Where: Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Australia

Title: "Exploring Discontinuous Preferences in Discrete Choice Experiments: The

Case of Cold-Water Corals in Norway"

Teaching

Teaching experience

2019 ECNU111 - Introductory Microeconomics

Institution: University of Stirling

Level: Bachelor

Role: Seminar lecturer

2018 Discrete Choice Experiments and Analysis in R

Institution: EIfER Europäisches Institut für Energieforschung EDF-KIT

Level: PhD course Role: Lecturer

2017 - 2018 SPF-0016 - Stated Preference Methods: State-of-the-Art Modeling

Institution: Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences

Level: PhD course Role: Lecturer

2017 SKO-151 – Forest Economics

Institution: Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences

Level: Bachelor Role: Lecturer

Teaching (continued)

2013 - 2015 SOK-3002 – Advanced Natural Resource Economics

Institution: UiT - The Arctic University of Norway

Level: Master

Role: Teaching assistant

2013 - 2015 SOK-2037 - Resource Economics

Institution: UiT - The Arctic University of Norway

Level: Bachelor

Role: Teaching assistant

2013 - 2015 SOK-2005 - Economics II

Institution: UiT - The Arctic University of Norway

Level: Bachelor

Role: Teaching assistant

2013 - 2015 SOK-1101 – Economics I

Institution: UiT - The Arctic University of Norway

Level: Bachelor

Role: Teaching assistant

2011 ECN-210 – Microeconomics I

Institution: The Norwegian University of Life Sciences

Level: Bachelor

Role: Teaching assistant

2011 ECN-211 – Microeconomics II

Institution: The Norwegian University of Life Sciences

Level: Bachelor

Role: Teaching assistant

Teaching qualifications

2020 LTHP300 - Evaluating practice

Institution: University of Stirling

Scope: 200 hours

2019 LTHP200 - Assessing Learning

Institution: University of Stirling

Scope: 200 hours

2019 LTHP100 - Designing and Facilitating Learning

Institution: University of Stirling

Scope: 200 hours

2018 Teaching in Higher Education - Basic course

Institution: Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences

Scope: 100 hours (3 weeks)

Teaching (continued)

2013 Teaching and learning in higher eduction

Institution: UiT - The Arctic University of Norway

Scope: 24 hours (3 days)

Academic visits (1 week or longer)

2018 Visiting researcher (4 weeks)

Where: Technical University of Delft, Transport and Logistics Group, Delft, The

Netherlands

Host: Professor Caspar Chorus

2018 Visiting researcher (3 weeks)

Where: University of Leeds, Institute for Transport Studies, Leeds, United Kingdom

Host: Professor Stephane Hess

2014 Visiting PhD Candidate (3 months)

Where: University of St. Andrews, School of Geography & Sustainable Development,

St. Andrews, United Kingdom Host: Professor Nick Hanley

Institutional responsibilities and professional roles

2019 -	Organizing committe for the 7 th International Choice Modelling Conference
	(ICMC)

2013 - 2016 Norwegian delegate to the European Council of Doctoral Candidates and

Junior Researchers (EURODOC)

2013 - 2016 Board member of the Association of Doctoral Organizations in Norway

(Stipendiatorganisasjonene i Norge, SiN)

2013 - 2014 Board chair of Tromsø Doctoral Students (TODOS)

Membership of Scientific Societies and Organizations

2019 - 1	present	Associate	Fellow of	of the	Higher	Education	Academy	

2020 - present American Economic Association (AEA)

2015 - present European Association of Environmental and Resource Economists

(EAERE)

Reviewing activities

Agribusiness; Bio-based and Applied Economics, Canadian Journal of Agricultural Economics; Environmental and Resource Economics; European Review of Agricultural Economics; Journal of Choice Modelling; Journal of Environmental Economics and Management; Journal of Forest Economics; Land Economics, Resource and Energy Economics